<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A famous victorie, atchiued in August last 1613. by the Christian gallies of Sicilia, against the Turkes Wherein were redeemed aboue a thousand Christian captiues, as many Turkes slaine, and aboue six hundred taken.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1613</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 12 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12218</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22528</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104565</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840298</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840298</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4785</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12218)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4785)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 860:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A famous victorie, atchiued in August last 1613. by the Christian gallies of Sicilia, against the Turkes Wherein were redeemed aboue a thousand Christian captiues, as many Turkes slaine, and aboue six hundred taken.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 9, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by W. White for] Th: Thorp,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1613.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sicily --  History, Naval --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Turkey --  History, Naval --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4785:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4785:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Famous Victorie, Atchiued in Auguſt laſt 1613. by the Chriſtian Gallies of <hi>Sicilia,</hi> againſt the Turkes.</p>
            <p>Wherein were redeemed aboue a thouſand Chriſtian Captiues, as many Turkes ſlaine, and aboue ſix hundred taken.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>Printed for <hi>TH: THORP. 1613.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:4785:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:4785:2"/>
            <head>A Famous Victorie, Atchiued in Auguſt laſt 1613. by the Chriſtian Gallies of <hi>Sicilia,</hi> againſt the Turkes.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>OW the <hi>Turke</hi> at firſt aſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to his greatneſſe, and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thence hath amplified and maintained it, chiefly by diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſion of <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Princes; I hold it needleſſe for mee to ſet foorth in writing, becauſe it is a truth commonly knowne, and generally confeſſed by all Writers: a matter much to be lamented, that thoſe Weapons which ought to haue been bent againſt the enemies of <hi>Chriſtians</hi> and their Religion, haue been ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtianly
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:4785:3"/>
and vnnaturally imployed in the effuſion of <hi>Chriſtian</hi> blood. Herevpon haue been erected thoſe glorious Trophies of many Victories, Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the <hi>Grand Siguior</hi> hath adorned his Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem.</p>
            <p>But I will not inſiſt any longer vpon this common place of our Calamities: Let vs ſee awhile, what fruites Concord hath produced, &amp; to what heighth of Honour ſhe hath aduanced her followers; that ſo by comparing the great loſſe and ignominie aryſing from the one, with the abundant profit &amp; renowne iſſuing from the other, we may all ioyne in one hearty prayer to God, That he would at length be pleaſed, to co-vnite the heartes of <hi>Christian</hi> Princes in one firme bond of Peace, to the replantation of his Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell in thoſe conquered Countries, and the extirpati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all <hi>Turciſme</hi> and Idolatrie.</p>
            <p>This was it, which loſt vs thoſe ample and goodly Prouinces in the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> wherein our Religion was at firſt propagated; and wherein ſo many Millions of <hi>Chriſtians</hi> ſince that time hitherto, haue been, and are reduced to moſt miſerable and inſupportable ſlauerie.</p>
            <p>But becauſe I ſtudy breuitie, as deſirous to draw neere the intended ſubiect of this Diſcourſe; it ſhall be ſufficient (among many others) to alleadge one or two examples for confirmation of this Truth.</p>
            <p>At ſuch time as that warlike <hi>Saladine,</hi> had by force inueſted himſelfe in the Kingdome of <hi>Syria,</hi> and ſubiected to his dominion <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> and the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:4785:3"/>
               <hi>Holy Land,</hi> the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Princes of theſe Weſterne partes, combined in a ſtrong league, and moued with an holy zeale of Gods glory, tranſported an Armie, vnder the conduct of <hi>Godfrey of Bulloine,</hi> for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couerie of that Countrie.</p>
            <p>Againſt this force of the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> the <hi>Saladine</hi> appoſed with all his power; and in many Conflictes, with variable ſucceſſe, for a long time maintained his partie: Meane while hee forgot not (like a ſubtile Foxe) by all poſsible meanes, to corrupt ſuch of the ſpeciall Commanders, as he thought moſt likely to be wonne to his purpoſe; if ſo, by diſſeuering the Chiefe of their ſecret Conſultations, he might make fruſtrate all their attempts.</p>
            <p>The ſumme is; his Plots fayled, and nothing ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to his wiſhed purpoſe. Hee relies therefore on his owne Strength; is fought withall, and defeated, and the Victorie ſo hotly purſued, that driuen hee is at length, to abandon the Kingdome, &amp; leaue it to the diſcretion of the victorious Conquerour.</p>
            <p>In his roome was that religious <hi>Godfrey</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throned: atfter whom, diuers <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Princes, for many yeares togeather, held the Soueraigntie there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, to the great aduantage and honour of <hi>Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> and the confuſion of their Enemies.</p>
            <p>Afterwardes, in the time of <hi>Richard</hi> the firſt, King of this Land, the <hi>French</hi> King then reigning, (excited with the like zeale of propagating our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and freeing that diſtreſſed Countrie from their mercileſſe Enemies) entred into firme League
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:4785:4"/>
with the ſayd <hi>Richard</hi> for the ſame purpoſe: Theſe Princes therefore with their ioynt forces, inuade the <hi>Turkes</hi> and winne many Victories, recouer moſt of their Townes from them, as <hi>Ioppe, Acon,</hi> and others; and in the end, expelling them from thoſe partes, reſtore a perfect Libertie to the oppreſſed Inhabitantes.</p>
            <p>By theſe meanes, haue diuers of our ancient Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces acquired true glorie, whileſt our Kingdome (beeing at peace in it ſelfe) was able and willing to imploy her forces againſt thoſe damned miſcreantes. But of this enough.</p>
            <p>It is now time that wee come to the purpoſe: wherein (according to my poore skill) I will limme out vnto you in a ſmall pourtrait, the true Patterne (ſome correſpondent circumſtances conſidered) of that famous Battaile of <hi>Lepanto;</hi> wherein the <hi>Turkes</hi> and <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> with their greateſt forces conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, who ſhould prooue the better men at Sea, and ought to haue the Commaund and Lordſhip thereof.</p>
            <p>In which fight, the moſt of the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Fleete was either loſt, or taken, and their Generall, with many other great Men, made Priſoners; beſides a world of ordinarie Souldiers ſlaine, and captiuated, But to our purpoſe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:4785:4"/>The Duke of <hi>Oſsuna,</hi> Vice-roy of <hi>Sicil,</hi> kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping good Watch vpon the Turkes procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, and knowing how much it behoued to vſe all circumſpection againſt ſo vigilant an enemy, for preuention of danger, and his owne better information, about the beginning of <hi>Auguſt</hi> laſt, ſent forth eight Gallies from <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lermo,</hi> well manned and prouided vnder com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of <hi>Don Octauio Taglia Via d' Arr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gona,</hi> to diſcouer or attempt ſomewhat in the <hi>Leu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t.</hi> Hauing all things therefore in a readineſſe, Hee happily ſet ſaile, and with a good gale came to <hi>Carigo:</hi> where hee ſoone vnderſtood that the Turkiſh Fleete ſome few dayes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore had put from <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> with thirty Gallies, and were bound for <hi>Rhodes,</hi> where they were to meete with ſixteene more, which as then lay wayting for them in the <hi>Negrepont;</hi> and that vpon the meeting of theſe Fleetes they ſhould make ſaile for <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria,</hi> there to bee imployed againſt certaine Rebels of that Countrey, that were lately re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolted from the Turkes obedience.</p>
            <p>Vpon this Aduertiſement hee put to Sea againe, and touched at ſome Iſlands of the <hi>Archipelago,</hi> where the ſame newes of the Turkiſh Fleete were againe confirmed. Hee made no long ſtay, but thruſt out againe, and ſome fewe houres after deſcried a Saile
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:4785:5"/>
Whereunto making with all ſpeede poſſible, hee found her to bee of the Iſle <hi>Macaria,</hi> demanding if they knewe any newes of the Turkes; They anſwered, that the day before, (at <hi>Zant</hi>) two Turkiſh Galliſh had taken from them fiue Barrels of Pitch; and that they reported for a truth, that the Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of <hi>Rhodes,</hi> the day before that Pitch ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, had ſent out twelue Gallies to tow cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Caramuſals, or great Veſſels, ouer the Channell of <hi>Samos,</hi> that they might bee the ſooner ready to take their Freight from the Carauan of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> and that for a more likely-hood that this was true, they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues (beſides thoſe two Gallies with whom they had Conference) had ſeene eight o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Gallies, towing the Caramuſals afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid.</p>
            <p>DON OCTAVIO hauing gotten this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence, preſently made to Sea-wards, and plying with ſtrength of Oares, and furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with a faire gale, held his courſe that day, and the next night for the other ſide to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the firme Land of <hi>Natolia.</hi> Thither hee came about the dawning, and at the Cape of <hi>Coruo</hi> met with all his Gallies, which were in ſafety.</p>
            <p>At day-breake hee ſet ſaile againe, and had not long coaſted, when hee might ken a farre
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:4785:5"/>
off, ten ſaile of Gallies, beeing part of thoſe twelue that had towed the Caramuſals: the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther two, as was afterwards reported, being ſent by the Turkiſh Generall to <hi>Scio.</hi> Hee had no ſooner got ſight of them, then hee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for their welcome, hauing a firme reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution to ouercome or bee taken. Diſtributing therefore in fit places, all weapons and mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition neceſſary, hee incouraged his Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, and furiouſly made forth againſt them.</p>
            <p>At the firſt hee had thought to haue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compaſſed them: but three of their Gallies keeping aloofe to ſea, made his purpoſe fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e.</p>
            <p>When the Fleetes were now come within reach of each other, the Ordinance on either ſide began to thunder, and the ſmall ſhot (like haile) flew aboord the Gallies.</p>
            <p>The two Generall Gallies made a furious en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter, and for the ſpace of halfe an houre, and vpwards, maintained a bloudy fight: du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring which time, <hi>Sinan</hi> the <hi>Beg</hi> of <hi>Cypras,</hi> Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall of the Turkiſh Fleete, ſtood aduanced in the poope of his Gally, to behold the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner thereof, and to giue directions as neceſsity required.</p>
            <p>In the end, after a ſharpe and terrible con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict, <hi>Don Octauio</hi> boorded the Turkiſh Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall in the Prow, and afterwards in the Poope,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:4785:6"/>
wherein the <hi>Sicillians</hi> made a wonderfull ſlaughter.</p>
            <p>In the meane while the other Gallies were not Idle, but with like violence aſſaulted each other.</p>
            <p>The victory fell to the <hi>Sicillians,</hi> with great execution done vpon the Turkes, and ſmall loſſe of their owne. Seuen of the Turkes Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies were preſently taken; two of them ranne a ſhore, and the Turkes leaping forth, ſaued themſelues in the mountaines: the other three fled to ſea-wards, and eſcaped.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Don Octauio</hi> hauing aſſured the victory, gaue thankes to God the Author thereof; and then gaue order to repaire his Gallies, which were no ſooner in a readineſſe, but with his owne Gallies, and thoſe that were taken, he ioyfully ſet forth, and made for <hi>Sicill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this fight, (beſides the ſeuen great Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Gallies which were taken) theſe men of quality were made priſoners; <hi>Sinan</hi> the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, a man of great account with the Turke: and <hi>Piali Baſsa</hi> the <hi>Beg</hi> of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> beeing ſonne to the ſame <hi>Haly Baſſa</hi> that was Generall at <hi>Lepanto:</hi> in whom I obſerue, that his Family and Name is (as it were) predeſtinated to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe the honor of Chriſtians with their ruine and captiuity.</p>
            <p>Many other men of great note were likewiſe
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:4785:6"/>
taken, who are not likely to bee redeemed for a little: ſixe or ſeuen hundred Turkes ſlaine, as many taken, and aboue a thouſand poore Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians freed from ſlauery.</p>
            <p>Thus haue I briefly related vnto you the ſumme of the victory; wherein if the phraſe be diſtaſtfull, let the truth of the matter ſupply that defect; And let the common ioy which wee ought all to receiue at the ouer-throw of our common ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, make ſome excuſe for my rudeneſſe, not affected with curioſity.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
